

London – UK

■ a.guedes@ucl.ac.uk • • alanlivio • in alanlivio • ■ alanlivio • ■ alanlivio • ■ alanlivio • ■ alanlivio

Shorbio

I am a Computer Scientist (PhD & Postdoc) interested in geometric Machine Learning (ML) for the next generation of immersive systems and graph-based data. My career can be seen threefold. In research, I worked on research Multimedia & ML projects, contributed to communities (Springer, ACM SIGMM and SBC WebMedia), and have been awarded research funding. In teaching, I co-supervised students, acted as a lecturer on under- and post-graduate courses, and organized workshops to promote student interest in public engagement. Last, I added value to the industry through open source and standards in TV forums (ITU-T SG16 and BR TV Forum).

Experiences

Work..

UCL, LASP Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML project

2021-today

Highlights: ACM SIGMM committees and workshop organizer; co-supervised undergrad students.

- SpheryStream project funded by EPSRC to Improve 360-video streaming with profile-based methods

PUC-Rio. TeleMidia Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML & Multimedia projects

2017-2020

Highlights: project PI; team leader; standards contributions; SBC WebMedia committees and workshop organizer (students for social impact); co-supervised under/postgrad students; postgraduate lecturer assistant.

- VideoMR project, funded by Microsoft & RNP to detect inappropriate content in video scenes;
- AML (Anti-Money Laundry) project, funded by BTG Bank, to detect financial transactions risk and anomaly detection;
- GT-RAP project, funded by RNP, to develop a blockchain-based system for academic certificates.

Dynavideo, TV Division

Software engineer

2012-2012

Highlights: multiple awarded social impact projects.
- Brasil4D project, funded by World Bank, to transmit interactive TV content with social features to low-income

families. Its results were published in a public report

Education.....

PUC-Rio

PhD. in Informatics. Thesis on Multimodal-multiuser support in multimedia scene descriptions 2013–2017 Highlights: thesis concepts used in SBTVD standard; industry committees.

- PUC-Rio Ginga, funded by PUC-Rio Software Licenses, to develop a reference implementation for TV manufacturers;
- SBTVD Conformance Test Suite project, funded by Brazilian Ministry of Science and Technology, to be used by TV manufacturers

UFPB

MSc. in Informatics. Thesis on Multi-device support in TV app stores

2010-2012

Highlights: thesis concepts used in the awarded Brasil4D project; undergraduate lecturer; project leader

- ${\sf GingaStore},$ funded by RNP, to design a broadband system to deliver TV applications;
- Art TVDI, funded by RNP, to design agile methods for TV applications development;

UFPB

BSc. in Computer Science. Final report on Component-based architecture for TV middleware 2005–2009

- Ginga CDN, funded by RNP, to develop reusable TV middleware components.
- Tutor on Analysis and design of Algorithms;
- Part-Time software developer at Dynavideo TV Division to prototype TV software in ST boards.

Research

Publications	
Google Scholar shows $>$ 40 published papers, $>$ 100 citations, h-index 6. See below recent and some	e selected
publications. Elsevier Book Chapter	2022
ACM Multimedia Systems.	2022
·	016, 2020
IEEE Symposium on Multimedia (ISM).	2020
SBC WebMedia 2020, 2020, 2020, 2021, 20	021, 2021
ACM Symposium on Document Engineering.	2019
IEEE Multimedia Signal Processing.	2019
Committees	
ACM, Special Interest Group on Multimedia	
-	020-today
 Multimedia conference: reviewer (2022), area chair (2022), reproducibility chair (2023) Multimedia Systems (ACM MM): MMVE review (2021, 2022, 2023) and demo chair (2022) Immersive Experiences (ACM IMX) conference: reviewer (2022) and area chair (2022) QoMex conference (ACM QoMEX): reviewer (2023) 	
BR Computing Society (SBC), Web&Mulimedia Commitee	
-	021-today
Reviewer and chairing - WebMedia conference reviewer (2017-today), chair of Undergrad workshop (2018), chair of Demos (2019-2022), and chair of Social Impact Workshop (2019-2022)	<i>017-today</i> Workshop
Springer	222
Reviewer - Journal of Multimedia Tools and Applications: reviewer (2022, 2023) - Iberoamerican Conference on TV Applications and Usability: reviewer (2020, 2021, 2022)	022-today
Brazilian TV Forum (SBTVD) Academic member at Technical Module contributing to TV middleware standards	2017-2021
International Telecommunication Union (ITU)	
Academic member at SG-16/Q13 contributing to IPTV middleware standards	2017-2021
Teaching	
UCL	/
	022-today
SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.	2018-2022
PUC-Rio	.010-2022
Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30)	2019
Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (>30).	2013
Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (>30)	2012
RNP ESR	2012
Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30)	2011
UFPB Lecturer and course design on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students (>1	15) 2010
Funding & Awards	
Microsoft&RNP	
Approved as PI in VideoMR project	2019

ACM	
SIGMM Travel Award for MMSys	2022
SIGHI Gary Marsden Travel Award for IMX	2022
SIGWeb Travel Award for DocEng	2019
Multiple TV associations	
FRIDA Innovative TV technological solutions award for Brasil4D project	2014
SET Conference award on Best TV interactivity solution for Brasil4D project	2013
PremioTV on Innovation and Creativity for Brasil4D project	2013
ITU	
IPTV Application Challenge User-friendliness for GingaStore project	2012
Skills	
Academic: Execute research agenda. Scientific and standard writing.	
Teaching: Course design. Presentation skills.	
Programing : Python, TensorFlow, Bash, C++, Lua, Java, JavaScript, Latex, Docker.	
Social: Good and empathic communication. Positive, make-it-happen, teamwork, lead-	by-example attitudes.
Languages: Portuguese (mother tongue), English (fluent), and Spanish (fluent).	
Training	
UCL	
Data Protection for Researchers; Fundamentals in Research Funding.	2022-2023
Nature	
Interpreting Scientific Results; Focus on Peer Review.	2022-2023
ITU	
ITU-T A.1: Working Methods of ITU-T Study Groups	2023

References

- Laura Toni, I.toni@ucl.ac.uk. Postdoc supervisor at UCL.
 Simone DJ Barbosa, simone@inf.puc-rio.br. PhD supervisor at PUC-Rio.
 Marcelo Moreno, moreno@ice.ufjf.br. ITU SG-16/Q13 and SBTVD collaborator.
 Roberto Azevedo, roberto.azevedo@disneyresearch.com. TeleMidia collaborator.